Guide to the Time Inc. Time Canada Ltd. Records 1954-1975, 1995-1999 MS 3009-RG 44
New-York Historical Society
Time Inc. Time Canada Ltd. Records
1954-1975, 1995-1999
New-York Historical Society
Time, inc.
MS 3009-RG 44
14 Linear feet in 14 record cartons
The materials in Time Canada Ltd. Records are all from the publishing and business side of the magazine, primarily from President Don Brown, and Managing Directors Lawrence Laybourne, Steve LaRue, and Bradley Gundy. There are a few folders of operating statements and from the Promotion Department.
Arrangement
Organized into four series:
Series I. President Don Brown Files
Series II. Managing Director Files
Series III. Financial Records
Series IV. Promotion Records
Biographical / Historical
Time Canada Ltd. is the subsidiary of Time Inc. that published the Canadian edition of Time. According to prepared answers in a Davey Committee folder in the Managing Director General Files, Time International of Canada Ltd. was incorporated in Canada in 1952 and is a wholly owned subsidiary of Time Inc. colloquially known as Time Canada. A letter to law firm Duquet MacKay, et al. in 1970 expresses the desire to change the legal name to TIME Canada Ltd. While the staff of Time Canada appear under several areas of the department head lists including Time Life International (TLI), Corporate International, and Time magazine, it looks as though it remained a subsidiary. A search of the Canadian government Federal Corporation Information website showed the subsidiary still active as of 2019 although the name was changed to TI Canada Ltd. in 2018.
Citation:
Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection are stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Scope and Contents
The materials in Time Canada Ltd. Records are all from the publishing and business side of the magazine, primarily from President Don Brown, and Managing Directors (publishers) Lawrence Laybourne, Steve LaRue, and Bradley Gundy. There are a few folders containing operating statements and from the Promotion Department.
The president's and managing directors' files focus on various attempts by the Canadian government to protect Canadian publications from foreign competition through changes to taxes and legislation, and Time Inc. arguing its case against being taxed or otherwise penalized.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Time Inc. in 2015.
Canada -- Commerce -- United States.; Corporations -- History.; Corporations -- New York (State) -- New York.; Corporation records.; Organization files.; Publishers and publishing -- Management; Publishers and publishing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Publishers and publishing -- United States -- History; United States -- Commerce -- Canada; Time, inc. -- Archives.; Time, inc. -- History.
- Series I. President Don Brown Files, 1995-1999; 2 Linear feet in 2 record cartons
  Biographical / Historical
  Don Brown retired in 2000 after working at Time Inc. since 1967. According to his Bio File, prior to his role as president, Brown served as Time Associate International Ad Director and Time Asia Publishing Director.
  In 1995, Parliament used Bill C-103, an act to amend the Excise Tax Act and the Income Tax Act to impose a high tax on advertising in a split-run edition of a periodical in an attempt to end split-run editions in Canada. "Split-run" is an edition with editorial content mainly from the foreign edition, but with advertising aimed at the Canadian market. In 1998, the Canadian government proposed Bill C-55 (Foreign Publishers Advertising Services Act) as a response to the 1993 attempt of Sports Illustrated Sports Illustrated to produce a "split-run" edition for Canada. The bill stated that foreign publishers could not print ads directed at the Canadian market.
  Citations:
  "Movers & Shakers." Strategy. March 27, 2000. Accessed August 16, 2019. http://strategyonline.ca/2000/03/27/28490-20000327/
  Time Inc. Bio Files, MS 3009-RG 2, New-York Historical Society.
  Thomas, Terrence J. Economics Division. (1998). Legislative History of Bill C-55. Title: Subtitle (LS-323E). Canada: Library of Parliament. http://publications.gc.ca/Collection-R/LoPBdP/LS/361/c55-e.htm
  Scope and Contents
  President Don Brown's files are rehoused binders about Canadian legislation and proposed legislation that affected Time Inc. publications. Records include correspondence, emails, press clippings, and copies of reports regarding legislation and presentations by Time Inc. making its case against the legislation.
  Arrangement
  Organized alphabetically.
  - Bill C-55 and Telemedia Communications Inc., 1999 (Offsite-box 3303, Folder 1)
  - Bill C55: World Trade Organization (WTO) Challenge, 1998 (Offsite-box 3303, Folder 2-9)
  - Bill C-55: World Trade Organization Challenge, 1998-1999 (Offsite-box 3304, Folder 1-8)
  - Bill C-103: Time Canada Ltd./Sports Illustrated Canada: Briefing Book, 1995 (Offsite-box 3304, Folder 9)
- Series II.A. Managing Director Lawrence Laybourne Files, 1954-1962; 6 Linear feet in 6 record cartons
  Lawrence Laybourne is listed in the Department Head Lists as the Managing Director of Time International of Canada Ltd. under Time Life International from 1960 to 1962. His files indicate he was in this position prior to 1960 and probably was not in it past 1962.
  A 1969 note in a Davey Committee folder in the Managing Director General Files explains the roles of the Managing Director (who is the publisher) and the Editor of Time Canada. The Managing Director oversees advertising sales, circulation, promotion, production, distribution, industry and public affairs and all budgeting.
  The Advertising Revenues Tax was proposed in 1956 as a 20% tax on ad revenues of Canadian editions of American magazines in order to protect Canadian publications from foreign competition. Time and Reader's Digest were the only two publications at the time to meet this definition. This tax was repealed. A continuation of this protection attempt came from the creation of the Royal Commission on Publications appointed in 1960 to examine periodical publications in Canada. This commission recommended in its report (known as the O'Leary Report named after the chair Grattan O'Leary) that any Canadian firm advertising in a Canadian edition of a foreign publication could not deduct those costs as business expenses.
  Citation:
  Time Inc. Reference Files, MS 3009-RG 3, New-York Historical Society.
  Lawrence Laybourne's files discuss advertising, effects of Canadian legislation on Time Canada, and public relations while Time Inc. disputes unfavorable legislation.
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: General, 1956-1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 1)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: 1930-1935 Tariff on Magazines, 1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 2)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: After June 18 and Repeal, 1958 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 3)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Aftermath: General, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 4)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Aftermath: Data for Use by Royal Commission, 1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 5)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Aftermath: Postmaster, 1959-1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 6)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Aftermath: Reader's Digest Suit, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 7)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Aftermath: Saturday Night Article, 1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 8)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Correspondence Up to Repeal, 1957-1958 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 9-10)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: News Clippings Prior to Repeal, 1956-1958 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 11)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Old Material, 1956-1959 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 12-13)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Press Comment on Repeal, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 14)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Repeal: Editorial Comment, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 15)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Repeal: House of Commons Debate, 1960 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 16)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Royal Commission Correspondence, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 3305, Folder 17)
  - Advertising Revenues Tax: Royal Commission Correspondence, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 1)
  - Berton, Pierre and Time, 1958-1959 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 2)
  - Canadian Editorial Costs, 1959 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 3)
  - Diefenbaker, John and Time, 1959-1962 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 4)
  - Dumping Definitions, 1960 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 5)
  - Dumping Duty on Magazines (Custom Duties), 1961-1962 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 6)
  - Editorial Operation: Montreal, 1961-962 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 7)
  - Frost, Leslie and Time, 1960 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 8)
  - Libel Suits, 1962 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 9)
  - Liquor Advertising, 1958-1962 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 10-11)
  - Luce, Henry R.: Correspondence, 1957-1962 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 12)
  - Magazine Promotion in Canada, 1959-1962 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 13)
  - Montreal Star and Time, 1958 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 14)
  - Printing in Canada, 1960-1962 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 15-16)
  - Promotion of the Magazine, 1957-1962 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 17)
  - Public Relations: Canadian Commentator January Article and Reply, 1959 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 18)
  - Public Relations: Correspondence on Canadian Content in Other Editions, 1957-1960 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 19-20)
  - Public Relations: Correspondence of Gibes at Time (Reader Complaints), 1957-1961 (Offsite-box 3306, Folder 21)
  - Royal Commission Report: Brief Submissions: The Reader's Digest Association (Canada) Ltd., 1960 (Offsite-box 3307, Folder 1-2)
  - Royal Commission Report: Brief Submissions: General, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 3307, Folder 3-8)
  - Royal Commission Report: Canadian Commentator Articles, 1961 (Offsite-box 3307, Folder 9)
  - Royal Commission Report: Canadian Facts Survey, 1961 (Offsite-box 3307, Folder 10)
  - Royal Commission Report: Canadian Publishers Arguments, 1958-1960 (Offsite-box 3307, Folder 11)
  - Royal Commission Report: CKLG Jack Webster Broadcast, 1961 (Offsite-box 3307, Folder 12)
  - Royal Commission Report: Correspondence: General, 1961-1962 (Offsite-box 3307, Folder 13)
  - Royal Commission Report: Correspondence with Goverment, 1961 (Offsite-box 3307, Folder 14-15)
  - Royal Commission Report: Correspondence with Time Inc., 1961 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 1)
  - Royal Commission Report: Financial and Questions for P. Michael Pitfield, 1960-1962 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 2)
  - Royal Commission Report: Laybourne's July Memo of Editorial Comment, 1961 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 3)
  - Royal Commission Report: Letters to Papers re: Editorials, 1961 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 4)
  - Royal Commission Report: Letters from Non-Subscribers, 1961 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 5)
  - Royal Commission Report: Letters from Subscribers, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 6-7)
  - Royal Commission Report: Mailing of Brief, 1960 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 8)
  - Royal Commission Report: Mailing of Report, 1961 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 9)
  - Royal Commission Report: Notes for Luce, 1961 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 10)
  - Royal Commission Report: Proposed Statements or Submissions, 1961 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 11)
  - Royal Commission Report: Publications of Hearings: Volumes 1, 8-9, 11-14, 21-22, 1960 (Offsite-box 3308, Folder 12-16)
  - Royal Commission Report: Publications of Hearings: Volumes 23-25, 1960 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 1-2)
  - Royal Commission Report: Report, 1961 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 3)
  - Royal Commission Report: Study on Canadian Attitudes to Interpretation of Commission Report, 1961? (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 4)
  - Royal Commission Report: Reader's Digest Article, 1961-1962 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 5)
  - Royal Commission Report: Scrapbooks on Editorials and Press Comment: Books I - VI, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 3310)
  - Royal Commission Report: Statements by Others, 1961-1962 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 6)
  - Royal Commission Report: Statements / Press Releases / Memoranda to Staff, 1954, 1961-1962 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 7)
  - Royal Commission Report: Submissions and Statemetns from Otehrs than Time, 1960-1961 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 8)
  - Royal Commission Report: Submissions by time International fo Canada, 1960? (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 9)
  - Royal Commission Report: Summary of Editorial Comments, 1961 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 10)
  - Royal Commission Report: Text of Resolutions Introduced by Nowlan, 1962 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 11)
  - Royal Commission Report: TV Show Background, 1961 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 12)
  - Royal Commission Report: Washington Post Time Ad, 1961 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 13)
  - Scott, John M.: Move to Canadian-based Operation, 1962 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 14)
  - Split Run Advertising, 1958-1962 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 15)
  - Ten Year Fix: Time International, 1960 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 16)
  - Time's Own Advertising (Ads in Other Publications), 1958-1961 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 17)
  - Toronto Building Project, 1961 (Offsite-box 3309, Folder 18)
- Series II.B. Managing Director Bradley Gundy Files, 1961-1965; 0.33 Linear feet in 5 folders
  Bradley Gundy is listed in the Department Head Lists as the Managing Director of Time International of Canada Ltd. under Time Life International in 1964 after serving as the Time Canada Advertising Manager. His files indicate he may have taken over this position from Lawrence Laybourne in 1963 and may have continued in it through 1965.
  The Canadian government created the Royal Commission on Publications in 1960 to examine periodical publications in Canada as an attempt to protect Canadian publications from competition by foreign media. This commission was also known as the O'Leary Commission after the chair Grattan O'Leary.
  Bradley Gundy's files focus on Canadian legislation that affected Time Canada.
  - Magazine Legislation: Memoranda to Staff, 1964 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 1)
  - O'Leary Commission: Clippings, 1963-1965 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 2-4)
  - O'Leary Commission: Report, 1961-1963 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 5)
- Series II.C. Managing Director General Files, 1958-1975; 5.25 Linear feet in 6 record cartons
  Steven LaRue is listed in the Department Head Lists as the Managing Director of Time International of Canada Ltd. from 1966 to 1972 although his records indicate he may have held the position longer.
  A 1969 note in a Davey Committee folder explains the roles of the Managing Director (who is the publisher) and the Editor of Time Canada. The Managing Director oversees advertising sales, circulation, promotion, production, distribution, industry and public affairs and all budgeting.
  General Files contain a mix of records from Managing Directors Bradley Gundy and Steve LaRue. Some folders have initials indicating which managing director's office they came from. These files were found mixed together.
  Records discuss advertising, effects of Canadian legislation on Time Canada, directors' and management meetings, and studies on subscribers.
  Organized into alphabetical order.
  - Bio Files: Barnes, Bernard, 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 6)
  - Bio Files: Bear, Charles, 1967 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 7)
  - Bio Files: Brumbaugh, David, 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 8)
  - Bio Files: Donovan, Hedley, 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 9)
  - Bio Files: Freeman, Gaylord A., Jr., 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 10)
  - Bio Files: Gates, Artemus, 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 11)
  - Bio Files: Heiskell, Andrew, 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 12)
  - Bio Files: Hoffman, Paul Gray, 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 13)
  - Bio Files: Larsen, Roy, 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 14)
  - Bio Files: Linen, James, 1963-1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 15-16)
  - Bio Files: Luce, Henry R., 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 17)
  - Bio Files: Luce, Henry, III, 1970 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 18)
  - Bio Files: Meek, Samuel Williams, 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 19)
  - Bio Files: Moore, Maurice T., 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 20)
  - Bio Files: Pace, Frank, Jr., 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 21)
  - Bio Files: Shepley, James R., 1970 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 22)
  - Bio Files: Stillman, Charles L., 1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 23)
  - British Columbia Liquor and Tobacco Legislation: Clippings, 1971 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 24)
  - Chicago Management Meeting, 1969 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 25)
  - Complimentary Subscriptions, 1964-1969 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 26)
  - Complimentary Subscription Cards and Replies, 1968-1969 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 27)
  - Continuing Study of Publication Audiences, 1961-1964 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 28-29)
  - Cover Art Show, 1963-1966 (Offsite-box 3311, Folder 30-31)
  - Cover Art Show, 1963-1966 (Offsite-box 3312, Folder 1-2)
  - Davey Committee: General, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 3312, Folder 3-9)
    In 1969, Senator Keith Davey proposed that the Canadian Senate establish a special committee to investigate ownership of the mass media in Canada focusing extensively on print journalism.
  - Davey Committee: Brief, circa 1970 (Offsite-box 3312, Folder 10)
  - Davey Committee: Briefs from Other Publications, 1970 (Offsite-box 3312, Folder 11)
  - Davey Committee: File Duplicates, 1969 (Offsite-box 3312, Folder 12)
  - Davey Committee: Press Comments, 1970 (Offsite-box 3312, Folder 13)
  - Davey Committee: Submission, 1970 (Offsite-box 3312, Folder 14)
  - Davey Committee: Submissions from Other Publications, 1970 (Offsite-box 3409, Folder 1)
  - Davey Committee: Submission Supplement, 1970? (Offsite-box 3409, Folder 2)
  - Davey Committee: Time Financial Statements, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 3409, Folder 3)
  - Directors' Meeting: General, 1966 (Offsite-box 3409, Folder 4-8)
  - Directors' Meeting: Briefing Books?, 1966 (Offsite-box 3409, Folder 9)
  - Directors' Meeting: Briefing Kit, 1966 (Offsite-box 3409, Folder 10)
  - Economic Outlook, 1958-1969 (Offsite-box 3409, Folder 11-14)
  - Economic Outlook, 1969 (Offsite-box 3313, Folder 1)
  - Editorial: News on Canada, 1966-1967 (Offsite-box 3313, Folder 2)
  - Editorial Conference: Quebec, 1964 February (Offsite-box 3313, Folder 3)
  - Editorial Conference: Maritimes, 1964 September (Offsite-box 3313, Folder 4)
  - Election Argument Settler, 1963 (Offsite-box 3313, Folder 5)
  - Expo 67 (Universal and International Exhibition of 1967), 1962-1967 (Offsite-box 3313, Folder 6-13)
  - History of Time Canada, 1967-1972 (Offsite-box 3313, Folder 14)
  - Legal: Duquet MacKay, 1969-1970 (Offsite-box 3313, Folder 15-16)
  - Time vs. Government: Action Plan, 1975 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 1)
    Time vs. Government documents the Canadian government's proposal to amend the Income Tax Act to eliminate tax breaks for businesses that place ads in Time Canada and Reader's Digest.
  - Time vs. Government: Association of Canadian Advertisers Brief, 1974 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 2)
  - Time vs. Government?: Clippings, 1970 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 3)
  - Time vs. Government: Clippings and News Reports, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 4-5)
  - Time vs. Government: Conference on Law and Contemporary Affairs, 1975 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 6)
  - Time vs. Government: Content Magazine: Swicker, Barry, 1975 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 7)
  - Time vs. Government: Data, 1974-1975 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 8)
  - Time vs. Government: Davey Committee Report, 1970 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 9)
  - Time vs. Government: Opinion Leader Mailing List, 1975 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 10)
  - Time vs. Government: Parliamentary Standing Committee: Brief Background, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 11-12)
  - Time vs. Government: Parliamentary Standing Committee: Rohmer and Time, 1974 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 13)
  - Time vs. Government?: Political Status of Time Canada, 1971 (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 14)
  - Time vs. Government: Report of the Royal Commission on Publications, 1961? (Offsite-box 3314, Folder 15)
  - Time vs. Government: Subscriber Attitude Study, 1975 (Offsite-box 3315, Folder 1-4)
  - Time vs. Government: Subscriber Mailing, 1975 (Offsite-box 3315, Folder 5)
  - Time vs. Government: The Sun: Reply to Peter Newman, 1975 (Offsite-box 3315, Folder 6)
  - Time vs. Government?: York University, 1970 (Offsite-box 3315, Folder 7)
- Series III. Financial Records, 1973-1975; 0.3 Linear feet in 6 folders
  The statements include statisics by month of issue size, types of pages (advertising or editorial), and an itemized list of revenue and expenditures.
  Organized chronologically.
  - Operating Statements, 1973-1975 (Offsite-box 3315, Folder 8-13)
- Series IV. Promotion Department, 1962-1974; 0.25 Linear feet in 3 folders
  Records includes correspondence between promotion department staff in New York, Toronto, and Montreal. Also found with the correspondence folders was a folder of tear sheets that says it is "incomplete." A tear sheet can be used by either an advertising department to prove that advertisements were published, or by writers as proof that their article was published. It is not clear what these tear sheets are trying to prove.
  - Editorial: General, 1962-1974 (Offsite-box 3315, Folder 14-15)
  - Editorial: Special Section on Leadership, 1974 (Offsite-box 3315, Folder 16)
  - Editorial: Tear Sheets, 1967 (Offsite-box 3315, Folder 17)